99. Social Contagion. We all understand that certain illnesses are contagious. We
don't share a drink with someone who has a cold. We also wash our hands after we
cough on them to keep from spreading germs. But we're discovering now that
germs aren't the only things that are contagious. Ideas and states of being can
be catching too. You must have noticed how you'll probably yawn if your friend
yawns, or if a friend tells you an angry story, you may feel yourself getting
angry. One person crying tends to make other people cry. This happens because of
our genes. When we watch someone else feel something or do something, the very
same parts of our brains that would control that emotion or action become
active. Human beings were designed to share each other's feelings and emotions.
Imitating other people's words and behavior is only natural for us. Imagine
that you have an overweight friend. This friend always orders too much food. When
you go out with him, you order a lot as well. Can you see how you'd end up
gaining weight that way? That's social contagion. If you have an overweight
spouse or sibling, the chances that you will be overweight increase. Or imagine
drinking and smoking. If your friends do those things, the chances that you will
try them increase. Understanding social contagion can help us live happier,
healthier lives. If you want to quit smoking, spend time with people who don't
smoke. Recognize when you and your friends are only encouraging each other
to complain. Once you know how other people affect you, you can surround
yourself with positive influences.